Guide to the John Sanford Martin papers, 1915-1958 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
John Sanford Martin papers 1915-1958 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Martin, John Sanford, 1886-1957
12 Linear Feet Approx. 8,602 Items
Newspaper editor from Winston-Salem, North Carolina.
Collection consists primarily of correspondence to and from John Sanford Martin, a newspaper editor from Winston-Salem, N.C. Letters from the 1930s to the 1940s provide information on economic and social problems in North Carolina from a number of committees on which Martin served. After 1940 there is much material on racial problems in Winston-Salem, and throughout North Carolina and the South. The correspondence from this period also reflects Martin's concern for the improvement of public education in North Carolina and his service on the North Carolina State Board of Education. Other papers relate to state and national politics, the New Deal, the Democratic Party, and the Baptist church. There are also some photographs in the collection. Significant correspondents include Josiah William Bailey, Joseph Melville Broughton, Josephus Daniels, Robert Lee Doughton, Drew Pearson, Strom Thurmond, and William Allen White.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Sanford Martin papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1959.
Collection Overview
The papers of John Sanford Martin, North Carolina newspaper editor and political figure, contain correspondence, 1912-1951, relating, for the most part, to Martin's long career as editor of the Journal and Sentinel, newspapers of Winston-Salem, North Carolina. Letters pertaining to national and state politics form an important part of this correspondence and concern the presidential election of 1928 and the split in the Democratic Party in North Carolina over the candidacy of Alfred E. Smith of New York; opposition to the state sales tax in North Carolina in the 1930s; Martin's leadership in s the liberal wing of the Democratic Party in North Carolina and his attempts to bring the state party in line with the New Deal; state and national contests in the elections of 1936; an attempt by Martin and liberal Democrats to keep conservative Democrats from obtaining a federal license for a radio station in Winston-Salem; and pressures put on North Carolina Democrats to join the Dixiecrats in 1948.
Martin's professional papers, 1936-1937, deal with the purchase of the Piedmont Publishing Company, owner of the Journal and the Sentinel by the Gordon Gray family of Winston-Salem, leaders of North Carolina's conservative Democrats; the decision to retain Martin as editor of the papers; and the establishment of a working relationship between Martin and Gordon Gray.
Correspondence from the period of World War II concerns the debate over the entry of the United States into the war, politics in North Carolina during the war, activities at home, and discussions about American policy after the war, including a confidential transcript of an interview with President Harry S. Truman in 1945 on future relations with the Soviet Union and the United Nations.
Letters from the 1930s to the 1940s provide information on economic and social problems in North Carolina from a number of committees on which Martin served. After 1940 there is much material on racial problems in Winston-Salem, and throughout North Carolina and the South. The correspondence from this period also reflects Martin's concern for the improvement of public primary and secondary education in North Carolina and his service on the North Carolina State Board of Education. The collection also includes the minutes of the board of education, 1943-1953, and memoranda on school finance, legislation, integration, curricula, teacher certification and salary, textbooks, school lunches, and student loans.
Material reflecting Martin's interest in the Baptist Church includes correspondence concerning various fund raising drives within the church, Wake Forest College and its relocation in WinstonSalem, Campbell College, North Carolina Baptist Hospital, and the purchase of the Biblical Recorder by the North Carolina State Baptist Convention, 1938-1939.
Printed material in the collection pertains to temperance, the R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company, Wake Forest University, Baptists in North Carolina, politics in North Carolina and the United States, and societies of professional journalists. There are a large number of Martin's speeches and editorials covering all aspects of his career.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Martin, John Sanford, 1886-1957
Bailey, Josiah William, 1873-1946
Broughton, J. Melville (Joseph Melville), 1888-1949
Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948
Doughton, Robert Lee, 1863-1954
Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969
Thurmond, Strom, 1902-2003
White, William Allen, 1868-1944
Baptist State Convention of North Carolina
Democratic Party (U.S.)
Education -- North Carolina
Journalists -- Political activity -- Southern States
New Deal, 1933-1939
North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
Southern States -- Race relations
United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century
Photographs
Contents of Collection
- John Sanford Martin papers, 1915-1958 and undated, (25 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1934 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1935-June 1936 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, July 1936-July 1937 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, August 1937-1938 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1939-September 1940 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, October 1940-1942 May (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, June 1942-August 1943 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, September 1943-May 1944 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, June 1944-August 1945 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, September 1945-June 1947 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, July 1947-1948 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1950-April 1951 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1951-May 1952 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1958 and undated (Box 15)
  - Legal papers, 1919-1941 and undated (Box 16)
  - Baptist Church papers, 1928-1950 and undated
  - Press releases, 1923-1950 and undated
  - Pictures, undated
  - Temperance papers, 1934-1936 and undated
  - Awards and other writings, 1940s-1950s and undated, (2 folders)
  - Sunday School lesson plans, undated (Box 17)
  - Speeches, 1915-1939 (Box 18)
  - Speeches, 1940-1953 (Box 19)
  - Speeches, 1954-1955 and undated (Box 20)
  - State Board of Education: papers, 1943-1953 (Box 21)
  - State Board of Education: papers, 1954-1956, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - State Board of Education: other, undated, (2 folders)
  - State Board of Education: printed materials, undated (Box 23)
  - Editorials, undated, (2 folders)
  - Editorials, undated (Box 24)
  - Clippings, printed materials, and volumes, undated (Box 25)